Guide to the Henry Graham Dakyns Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Henry Graham Dakyns Papers
1846-1999
GEN MSS 698
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
10
(18 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, photographs, financial papers, printed material and other related papers, created and accumulated by Henry Graham Dakyns and the Dakyns family.
Dakyns, Henry Graham, 1838-1911
General note
This finding aid describes a collection that has been acquired by the library in discrete segments over time. The narrative sections of the finding aid provide information about the content and context of the collection. The Collection Contents section provides a general description and in some instances a box or folder listing of the various acquisitions of the collection. The >Processing Notes section provides information about the way and extent to which the library has processed this collection. The Arrangement section provides information about how material within this collection is organized and tips on how to locate material across various acquisitions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Andrew G. Dakyns on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2006-2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Henry Graham Dakyns (1838-1911)
Henry Graham Dakyns was born on the island of St. Vincent in the West Indies on 1 August 1838. His father, Thomas Henry Dakyns (1803-1874) was a physician, who later left St. Vincent and became an attorney, running several estates. He later moved to England after the decline of the sugar trade in 1845 and was made Sub-Treasurer of the Middle Temple (Inn of Court) in London.
Thomas Dakyns had married his half-cousin, Harriet Dakyns née Dasent (1814-1868) in 1834. They had six sons: John Roche Dakyns (1836-1910), Henry Graham Dakyns (1838-1911), Bury Irwin Dakyns (1842-1918), Charles Stewart Dakyns (b.1844), Thomas Arnold Dakyns (1847-1910) and George Doherty Dakyns (1856-1939).
Henry Graham Dakyns attended Rugby School from 1850 to 1856 and Trinity College, Cambridge from 1857 to 1860. Upon graduation in 1860, Henry Graham Dakyns became the tutor of Alfred, Lord Tennyson's two sons: Hallam Tennyson (1852-1928) and Lionel Tennyson (1854-1886). He held this position at Farringford, Isle of Wight until 1861. In September 1862, he was appointed Assistant Master of Classics at Clifton College, Bristol.
Henry Graham Dakyns married Margaret Cay née Pirie (1846-1908) in 1872. She was the widow of Charles Hope Cay. They had three children, Henry Graham Dakyns (1874-1937), Margaret Frances Dakyns (1877-1960), and Arthur Lindsay Dakyns (1883-1941).
From 1881 until 1883, Henry Graham Dakyns took a sabbatical in Greece to work on his edition of the Complete Works of Xenophon. In December 1889, he retired from Clifton College, moving to Higher Coombe, Haslemere in 1891. He co-edited the Collected Poems of T.E. Brown (1900) with Horatio Brown & W.E. Henley and the Golden Treasury Selected Poems of T.E. Brown (1908) with Horatio Brown. He also contributed the chapter "Tennyson, Clough & the Classics" to Tennyson & his Friends (1911), edited by Hallam, Lord Tennyson, Macmillan & Co. Ltd.
Henry Graham Dakyns died of a heart attack at Haslemere station on 28 June 1911 at the age of 72.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, photographs, financial papers, printed material and other related papers, created and accumulated by Henry Graham Dakyns. Correspondence often contains letters both sent and received by Dakyns, since he made a point of asking for his own letters to be returned in certain cases. Primary correspondents include his immediate and extended family, the Alfred, Lord Tennyson family, with whom he worked, and friends, colleagues, and pupils from Trinity College, Cambridge and Clifton College, Bristol, including John Addington Symonds and Horatio F. Brown, among others. Also found is extensive correspondence between various members of the immediate Dakyns family, including Dakyns, his wife Margaret Elsie Dakyns, his eldest son Henry Graham Dakyns, his daughter Margaret Frances Dakyns, and his youngest son Arthur Lindsay Dakyns.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four groupings: I. August 2006 Acquisition. II. October 2007 Acquisition. III. November 2008 Acquisition. IV. December 2009 Acquisition.
Material within this collection has been organized by acquisition reflecting the fact that the collection has been acquired in increments over time.
Researchers should note that material within each acquisition overlaps with and/or relates to material found in other acquisitions. For instance, correspondence can be found in all three groupings. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers will need to consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section.
Researchers should also note that similar material can be arranged differently in each acquisition, depending on how the material was organized when it was received by the library.
Brown, Horatio F. (Horatio Forbes), 1854-1926; Dakyns, Arthur Lindsey; Dakyns, Bury Irwin; Dakyns, Charles Stewart; Dakyns, George Doherty; Dakyns, Harriet; Dakyns, Henry Graham, 1838-1911; Dakyns, Henry Graham, 1838-1911; Dakyns, John Roche; Dakyns, Margaret Elsie; Dakyns, Margaret Frances; Dakyns, Thomas Arnold; Dakyns, Thomas Henry; Irwin, Sidney T. (Sidney Thomas), -1911; Mozley, John Rickards; Symonds, John Addington, 1840-1893; Tennyson, Hallam Tennyson, Baron, 1852-1928; Tennyson, Lionel Hallam Tennyson, Baron, 1889-1951; Clifton College (Bristol, England); Trinity College (University of Cambridge)
- August 2006 Acquisition, circa 1863-1893; 1; (2 boxes)
  General note
  Formerly classed as Uncat MSS 891.
  Scope and Contents
  This portion of the collection contains correspondence between John Addington Symonds and Henry Graham Dakyns, with related correspondence from the Symonds family and writings by John Addington Symonds, including poetry.
  - Writings, 17 (Box 1)
  - Symonds, Jane Catherine (Box 1)
  - Symonds, John Addington (Box 1)
  - Green, Charlotte Symonds (Box 1)
  - North, Marianne (Box 1)
  - Symonds, "Lotta" (Box 1)
  - Symonds/Vaughan, "Madge" (Box 1)
  - Symonds, Janet (Box 1)
  - Green, T.H. (Box 1)
  - Symonds, John Addington - undated and unpublished letters (Box 1)
  - Symonds, John Addington - published letters, 1863-1892; 10 (Box 2)
- October 2007 Acquisition, circa 1846-1999; 2; 5.4; (6 boxes)
  Formerly classed as Uncat MSS 974.
  Arrangement
  Material arrived in twenty-seven ring binders, organized according person and, in once instance, according to format. Material was removed from the binders and was largely maintained in the order in which it was received. In the file list below, there is a single entry for each person, even when the material associated with that person was housed in more than one ring binder.
  This portion of the collection consists of correspondence between Henry Graham Dakyns and his immediate family and extended family, the Alfred, Lord Tennyson family and friends, colleagues and pupils from Trinity College, Cambridge and Clifton College, Bristol.
  - Dakyns, Thomas Henry, 1846-1872; 8 (Box 3)
  - Dakyns, Harriet, circa 1847-1867; 8 (Box 3)
    Includes various other family correspondence.
  - Dakyns, John Roche, 1860-1910; 15 (Box 3)
  - Dakyns, John Roche - Memorabilia, 1910-1999; 6 (Box 4)
    Includes various correspondence from the decendents of the Dakyns family.
  - Dakyns, Thomas Arnold, 1862-1910; 2 (Box 4)
  - Dakyns, Bury Irwin, 1861-1910; 2 (Box 4)
  - Dakyns, Charles Stewart, 1861-1930; 5 (Box 4)
    Includes Charles Stewart Dakyns correspondence to his niece, Frances, dating from 1917 to 1930.
  - Dakyns, George Doherty, 1868-1918; 6 (Box 4)
    Includes George Doherty Dakyns correspondence to Henry Winifred (30 December 1918).
  - Dakyns Extended Family, circa 1860s-1909; 3 (Box 4)
    Includes the will and estate papers of John Bury Dasent, 1888.
  - Hall, Lucy, 1887-1911; 2 (Box 4)
  - Alfred, Lord Tennyson Family, 1861-1911; 8 (Box 5)
    Includes Tennyson memorabilia, collected by Henry Graham Dakyns.
  - Trinity College, Cambridge, 4 (Box 5)
    Includes letters and memorabilia relating to Henry Graham Dakyns from friends and colleagues at Trinity College, Cambridge, including members of the 'Initial Society' and some of their essays. Also included are letters from Henry Sidgwick, Janet Catherine Symonds, her daughter 'Madge' and Sarah Frances 'Fanny' Alleyne.
  - Clifton College, Bristol, circa 1860s-1910s; 5 (Box 5)
    Includes letters to Henry Graham Dakyns from Headmasters and Staff at Clifton College, Bristol.
  - Irwin, Sidney Thomas, 1885-1907; 5 (Box 5)
  - Mozley, John Rickards, 1864-1911; 19 (Box 6)
  - Pupils at Clifton College, Bristol, 1865-1907
    - Carré, Arthur Augustus, 1865-1868; 3 (Box 6)
    - Boyle, Cecil William, 1872-1907; 2 (Box 6)
    - Howlett, William F., Jr. and William Howlett Sr., 1866-1886 (Box 6)
    - Moor, Edward Norman Peter, 1882-1891 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous Letters, 1857-1910; 5 (Box 7)
    Includes letters to Henry Graham Dakyns from a wide variety of friends, colleagues and acquaintances.
  - Memorabilia, circa 1850s-1925; 4 (Box 7)
    Includes family photographs, an 'In Memoriam' for Henry Graham Dakyns, as well as various obituaries, his Rugby School Reports, letters regarding his Cambridge degree, a selection of invoices/receipts dating from 1856, letters in German, a copy of a letter Henry Graham Dakyns wrote to Walt Whitman, and 25 letters from Macmillan & Co. Also includes an 'In Memoriam' and various obituaries regarding Alfred Denis Godly (1856-1925), who was the son-in-law of Henry Graham Dakyns.
  - Brown, Horatio Forbes, 1889-1911; 14 (Box 7)
  - Family of Margaret Elsie Dakyns née Pirie, circa 1870s-1911; 2 (Box 7)
  - Pirie Family, circa 1870s-1911; 2 (Box 7)
  - Pirie Family, circa 1870s-1911; 5 (Box 8)
- November 2008 Acquisition, circa 1860-1988; 3; (8 boxes)
  Formerly classed as Uncat MSS 1142.
  Arranged into three series: Correspondence, Family Wills and Probate Papers, and Photograph Albums.
  This portion of the collections consists of correspondence between various members of the immediate Dakyns family, including Henry Graham Dakyns, his wife Margaret Elsie Dakyns, his eldest son Henry Graham Dakyns, his daughter Margaret Frances Dakyns, and his younger son, Arthur Lindsay Dakyns, and some correspondence with extended family; as well as family photograph albums, material relating to Arthur Lindsay Dakyns, and family wills and probate papers.
  - Correspondence
    - Letters from Henry Graham Dakyns to His Wife, Margaret Elsie Dakyns (#1), 1874-1907; 8 (Box 9)
    - Letters from Margaret Elsie Dakyns to Her Husband, Henry Graham Dakyns (#2), 1900-1907; 3 (Box 9)
    - Letters from Arthur Lindsay Dakyns to His Parents, Henry Graham Dakyns and Margaret Elsie Dakyns (#3), 1888-1908; 3 (Box 9)
    - Letters from Arthur Lindsay Dakyns to His Parents, Henry Graham Dakyns and Margaret Elsie Dakyns (#3), 1888-1908; 4 (Box 10)
    - Letters from Arthur Lindsay Dakyns to His Father, Henry Graham Dakyns (#4), 1909-1911; 4 (Box 10)
    - Material relating to Arthur Lindsay Dakyns (#4)
      - Memoir of the life of Arthur Lindsay Dakyns by His Daughter, Jane Rosalind Dakyns, 1988 (Box 10)
      - Obituary of Patrick Monkhouse (Box 10)
      - Letter Regarding Birth of Arthur Lindsay Dakyns, 1883 (Box 10)
      - "The Little Ruby Stone", A Story by Arthur Lindsay Dakyns, and Various Cartoons (Box 10)
      - Arthur Lindsay Dakyns's Diary, 1895 (Box 10)
      - Cartoons from "Punch" by Arthur Lindsay Dakyns (Box 10)
      - Balliol College Documents: letter regarding entrance exam, matriculation certificate, and testimonials in favor of Dakyns, 1902, 1906-1907 (Box 10)
      - Arthur Lindsay Dakyns's Paper on Gorki and Letter from Tom Dehn, 1907 (Box 10)
      - Thank You Letter from Workers' Educational Association, 1914 (Box 10)
      - Letter from M. Trocmé to Arthur Lindsay Dakyns and Letters from Dakyns to his brother Henry Dakyns, Mrs. Mansbridge, and his sister Frances Dakyns, 1914-1915 (Box 10)
      - Notebook and Various Paper Clippings (Box 10)
    - Letters from Henry Graham Dakyns to his son, Arthur Lindsay Dakyns (#5), 1884-1910; 2 (Box 11)
    - Letters from Henry Graham Dakyns to his elder son, Henry Graham Daykns (#5) (Box 11)
    - Letters from Henry Graham Dakyns to his daughter, Margaret Frances Dakyns (#5) (Box 11)
    - Letters from Margaret Elsie Dakyns to her son, Arthur Lindsay Dakyns (#5) (Box 11)
    - Letters from Margaret Frances Dakyns to her brother, Arthur Lindsay Dakyns (#5) (Box 11)
    - Letters from the Cay Family and the Pirie Family (#5) (Box 11)
    - Letters from Henry Graham Dakyns (son) to his parents, Henry Graham Dakyns and Margaret Elsie Dakyns (#6), 1884-1910; 3 (Box 11)
    - Letters from Henry Graham Dakyns (son) to his sister, Margaret Frances Dakyns (#6) (Box 11)
    - Letters from Henry Graham Dakyns (son) to his brother, Arthur Lindsay Dakyns (#6) (Box 11)
    - Letters to Henry Graham Dakyns (son) from Stanley V. Makower (#6) (Box 11)
    - Letters from Amy Cay to her mother and stepfather, Margaret Elsie Dakyns and Henry Graham Dakyns (#6) (Box 11)
    - Letters from Margaret Frances Dakyns to her parents, Henry Graham Dakyns and Margaret Elsie Dakyns (#6) (Box 11)
    - Letters from H.F. Fox to Henry Graham Dakyns regarding Arthur Lindsay Dakyns's stay at Headington Hill, Oxford (#6) (Box 11)
    - Letter from Maurice Woods to Arthur Lindsay Dakyns (#6) (Box 11)
    - Letters from Arthur Lindsay Dakyns to his sister, Margaret Frances Dakyns (#7), 1916-1939; 3 (Box 11)
    - Letters from Arthur Lindsay Dakyns to his brother and sister-in-law, Henry Graham Dakyns (son) and Winifred Dakyns (#7), 1932-1934 (Box 12)
    - Letters from Winifred Dakyns to her sister-in-law, Margaret Frances Dakyns (#7), 1902-1938 (Box 12)
    - Letters from Margaret Isobel Dakyns to her sister-in-law, Margaret Frances Dakyns (#7), 1934-1939 (Box 12)
    - Letters from Sir Sidney P. Waterlow to Margaret Isobel Dakyns (#8), 1942-1943 (Box 12)
    - Letters from Enid Dakyns to Margaret Frances Dakyns (#8), 1927-1929 (Box 12)
    - Letter from Enid Dakyns to Arthur Lindsay Dakyns (#8), 1933 (Box 12)
    - Letters from Cecco to Margaret Frances Dakyns written during the First World War (#8) (Box 12)
    - Letters between Sir Donald Francis Tovey to Margaret Frances Dakyns (#8) (Box 12)
    - Letters between C. Skinner to Margaret Frances Dakyns (#8), 1919-1920 (Box 12)
    - Letters from Malcolm and Kitty Muggeridge to Margaret Isobel Dakyns (#8), 1970-1982 (Box 12)
    - Letters to Henry Graham Dakyns from Park Nelson, Solicitors (#8), 1874-1876 (Box 12)
    - Letters to Henry Graham Dakyns from Palmer and Smith, Solicitors (#8), 1888-1889 (Box 12)
  - Family Wills and Probate Papers (#8), 3 (Box 12)
  - Photograph Albums
    - "Photos" (#9), originals and reproductions of family photographs with typescript identifications (Box 13)
    - Photographs, exterior and landscape scenes (#12) (Box 13)
    - Photographs of India with manuscript identifications (#10), circa 1909 (Box 14ov)
    - Photographs (#11), Reproductions of images from Egypt, Japan, and India (includes letter to Graham from Alice recounting travels in Kashmir), circa 1909 (Box 14ov)
    - Album (#13), containing reproductions of art work, postcards, writings, 1860s (Box 15ov)
    - Cartes-de-visite (#14), 1860s (Box 15ov)
    - Cartes-de-visite (#15), 1860s (Box 16)
    - Cartes-de-visite (#16), 1860s (Box 16)
- December 2009 Acquisition, 1874-1880; 4; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  This portion of the collections consists of five books by John Addington Symonds. Each are signed and contain mansucript notes and annotations.
  - Symonds, John Addington
    - New And Old: A Volume Of Verse. Smith, Elder & Co., 1880 (Box 17)
      This book contains one full page of pencilled notes at the front entitled "Mss given me by JAS" and a pencilled poem on the final page. Both are in Henry Graham Dakyns' hand.
    - Many Moods: A Volume Of Verse. Smith, Elder & Co., 1878 (Box 17)
      This book contains on full page of pencilled notes at the front entitled "Mss given me by JAS". It is in Henry Graham Dakyns' hand.
    - Renaissance In Italy: The Revival Of Learning. London: Smith, Elder & Co., 1877 (Box 17)
      This book contains notes on the final page in John Addington Symond's hand giving literary references.
    - Sketches In Italy And Greece. London: Smith, Elder & Co., 1874 (Box 18)
      This book contains a small number of pencilled notes at the front, entitled "Mss given me by JAS". It is in Henry Graham Dakyn's hand.
    - The Sonnets Of Michael Angelo Buonarroti And Tommaso Campanella. Smith, Elder, & Co., 1878 (Box 18)
      This book contains one full page of pencilled notes at the front, entitled "Mss given me by JAS". It is in Henry Graham Dakyn's hand.